BENJAMIN VAN VLIET

- +61 423 065 456
- Benjamin.g.vanvliet@gmail.com
- Perth, Australia
- in /in/benvanvliet/

SUMMARY

Currently leading BHP's Innovation Centre, which is a flagship proving ground where new technology services are designed and developed in readiness for global scaling.

My passion is in product leadership, which has been lived and exemplified within taking over a portfolio in its infancy and growing it with an exceptional team of product owners, designers, and developers. I have been a part of a team that discovers, incepts, and delivers new services that improve the lives of our customers in BHP's operations. This has been instrumental in shifting a legacy corporate IT mindset and paving the way for strategy and direction setting around concepts and approaches including being design-led, cloud-native, and customer-centric.

In the past, I was part of BHP's Technology Strategy and Innovation leadership team, where I joined with a vision to help establish a more progressive global Enterprise Architecture capability. My background is as a technology consultant, starting in ERP functional work before shifting focus to develop and lead work in software development, system integration, process improvement, and operating model definition.

KEY SKILLS

Portfolio design

Scaling agile delivery practices, product team inception, opportunity management, enabling innovation in high-friction enterprises, establishing product ownership as a discipline.

Architectural thinking

Articulating complex issues, solving problems, and making difficult decisions to meet business objectives.
Considering implementation costs, technology requirements and users experiences.

Product leadership

Domain driven design, experimental approaches to product development, continuous delivery practices, user experience and service design.

Stakeholder management

Experience developing highlevel relationships with senior stakeholders.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Digital Transformation Manager

Mar. 2018 – Present

BHP Strategy & Innovation (14 direct reports, 62 staff) Perth, Australia

- Product manager for a delivery organisation of software and hardware engineers, technical leads, service designers and product owners, leading key strategic business outcomes both from sensor and actuator to software, and across the mining value chain from resource geology to train loading,
- Integrated and rebuilt a disparate portfolio of technology pilot work into a product-oriented delivery structure aligned to customerfacing OKRs and a coherent architecture,
- Launched many new services including BHP's 'live mine' tool that delivers faster and higher-quality schedules and decisions for mine load and haul operations. Thus, resulting in better mining fleet utilisation throughout BHP's operations.

Business Architecture Principal

Dec. 2016 - Mar. 2018

BHP Technology Strategy & Innovation
Singapore | Santiago, Chile | Brisbane, Australia

- Brought into the Digital Strategy team to build a world-class
 Enterprise Architecture practice, later relocating to Singapore and
 working across Chile, Australia and the USA with Technology VPs
 and C-suite executives to embed the work and architecture mindset
 and approaches globally,
- Worked to manage and direct large and complex technology and architectural change including embedding the business architecture framework into all technology project design work.

KEY SKILLS cont.

Technical leadership

Legacy architecture remediation, cloud-native software development, integration of emerging technologies including IIoT hardware and services.

Knowledgeable

Possessing strong product, technology, and industry knowledge.

EDUCATION

Queensland University of Technology (QUT)

Brisbane, Australia

Bachelor of Information Technology (with Distinction) 2007 – 2010

Bachelor of Business (with Distinction) 2007 – 2010

Central Queensland University (CQU)

Queensland, Australia

Graduate Diploma of Information Systems – Business Analysis (with Distinction) 2012

CERTIFICATIONS

AWS Solution Architect Associate 2020

Certified Scrum Product Owner (CSPO) 2018

PRINCE2 Foundation 2009

Justice of the Peace (Qualified), Queensland 2009

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE cont.

Technology Project Manager / Tech Lead / Solution Architect

BHP Billiton Jan. 2016 – Dec. 2016

Brisbane, Australia | Moranbah, Australia

- Led BHP's first efforts in developing a service blueprint, distributed architecture and trial to remotely manage fixed plant processes and operations through publicly available cloud PaaS,
- Developed solution architecture for and roadmaps to integrate train load-out operations and the truck, shovel, and dragline fleet management through a more decoupled and service-oriented landscape,
- Led the development of a novel wireless plant water quality sensor that laid the blueprint for later work on Industrial Internet of Things services.

Asset Portfolio Strategic Planner – Technology and LogisticsBHP Billiton Mitsubishi Alliance (BMA)

Jan. 2015 – Jan. 2016
Brisbane, Australia

- Responsible for the BHPB Coal business technology planning roadmap and strategy,
- Also owned planning and capacity management for the logistics portfolio, which included over 60 contracts for rail services, rail network access, intracompany agreements and use of bulk commodity ports,
- Led improvement initiatives resulting in many tens of millions of dollars in productivity and cost out benefits and in securing more than AUD\$1 billion of rail and port access as part of long-term planning.

Consultant - Business and Systems IntegrationJan. 2011 – Dec. 2014

Accenture

Brisbane, Australia

- Delivered numerous complex and successful people, process, and systems initiatives for resource sector clients,
- Managed teams to deliver mobile and custom software delivery, operational effectiveness assessments, ERP deployments, managed service delivery, operating model definition and design, technology strategy and process interventions,
- Deep and global expertise as a SAP Plant Maintenance consultant working across process design, system integration, testing, data, business continuity planning and change management aspects of both global ERP implementation, upgrades and retrofit deployments.